good morning kahshanna thanks so much
for making time for this conversation
and really looking forward to it
normally I ask people to introduce
themselves with a whole life story but I
feel like we could get to that later
also many people already know you
because we've talked before and I would
just love to take this call to from you
a wealth of experience of having worked
with Jen for so long now first in
general with the Eco village movement
and in recent years really helping to
lead this diverse group of people
working in in a very horizontal way into
its its future for quite some time now
and you're just about to step out of
that so I think it would be wonderful to
have you recount a little bit from your
perspective and also how you connected
to it first the story of the global eco
village network because I know something
about it but many people might not
thanks Daniel yeah it's lovely to be
here with you for the series first you
know I'm really I'm so with you that
this is the age where we need to shift
from degenerative to regenerative
cultures you know and lovely to bring
that piece of the puzzle
you know the mini piece that is my own
personal contribution my own life but
then the bigger slightly bigger piece of
the puzzle there is also the
contribution of the global eco village
Network we've which I just feel so
joyful and honored to have been a part
of and for some reason it intertwined
quite early in my life so it's the
impulse to move away from individual
protest against social injustice and
understanding that actually we need to
come together I think also as you know I
grew up in South Africa
then I started being an activist against
the apartheid system quite early on and
that was quite a lonely place to be in
life so I think many people who are very
attractive to the global eco village
Network the promise of community might
also be people who have changed their
lives a lot who have been looking for
what is true for me how can I contribute
and might have felt quite lonesome at
times on that journey so I was
definitely one of those people feeling
quite lonesome at times so I started
looking for community very early on and
there's the story of me which is a
reality when I was younger of walking up
the coast in South Africa on a
pilgrimage and you know very strong
experience of being out alone in an
atmosphere of violence an incredible
natural beauty and in that atmosphere
just finding back to my inner courage
but also to my trust in life and at the
end of that journey ending up in parts
of Jones where a community of people was
living together black and white people
and that was a changing point a complete
turning point in my life because I went
on that journey from a deep place of not
knowing what to do anymore
I had studied cultural anthropology and
linguistics I had been a political
activist with so science activism and
none of it really hit the point for me
and the moment I was in this community I
started being incredibly awake and
curious and it was as if I had found
something but I couldn't quite name it
and it took me years to name it you know
that it's about believing that we can
create the dream of the future now
if we do it together and we need each
other that we cannot do it alone and
that was a deep truth that I I i somehow
soaked up more through my cells than my
senses that my brain and it took me a
long time before I could bring words to
it but from that experience also this
concept of not fighting the existing
structures but actually creating the new
structures within you know if you we
speak about nested complexity which had
what happens to complex systems when we
bring in a completely new impulse right
and how can we change complex systems
through that so moving from that back to
Europe I started exploring this network
of you know through the less-traveled
class of mouth-to-mouth inspiration and
just found communities everywhere you
know in the Pyrenees and Israel in India
in Egypt even you know it was just
wherever I travel the world was full of
new communities sprouting up people
creating these lifestyles but also in a
very very hidden way and I decided quite
early on that I wanted to live in
community so in 1995 when the jhen
conference happened I was actually just
moving into pregnancy with my son and I
knew about this conference happening so
my friends from the community at that
point I was staying in Germany and my
friend silca and dieter dieter Halbach
silca hoc Meier who have been very close
they were cofounders of similan them but
also cofounders of the German equivalent
movement at that time they both came so
they shared the stories about even at
that time that there were only three
people from Africa present present at
that founding conference and when it was
called a global network they stood up
and said you know what about us our
voice isn't really here you know how can
you call this grow
so I was really aware and I went to some
of the earliest earliest gatherings of
djenne in 1997 I believe in 1998 there
was a gathering in the German community
of the European part of the network and
I found it exciting you know but also it
was very small you know at that time the
gathering was like 30 people the
European gathering was 30 people or 40
people coming together and it grew you
know my engagement really deepened
through moving to a bigger eco village
in Germany getting involved in the
founding of Gaia education the writing
of the curriculum but then my real
entrance came in a very surprising
moment which was 2008 when I had
co-facilitated co-hosted actually with
Francois Eastman and Thomas Huebel a big
conference in Berlin on the on the topic
of the power of collective wisdom which
had many people from communities in
Europe come to that conference and
afterwards I went back to my home Eco
village seed ininin and there was a
European gathering of the European
Network at that point around 70% 2008
2008 okay okay yeah yeah 2008 and at
that gathering I spoke out I was
verbally outspoken about the fact that
still the African networks and the
Middle Eastern networks were kind of
folded into the name of Jan Europe
Africa and Middle East but that the
funds that came from Gaia trust were
staying within Europe right because that
was the only network that was
functioning and I ended up being elected
as president of Jan Europe at that
gathering which was a complete surprise
to me and I'm sure to many others but it
just opened this door into an active
from being a trainer a consultant for a
community creation to sunny bring to the
table my my master is also an
organizational development which yeah
and from a net that it is just because
that was after you'd already really
built up a very strong series of
equalities and education programs ins
even Linden with the German government
and and had also brought people from
Africa how did that happen afterwards
know that that had happened before the
first course
I think was 2006 or 2007
I think 2006 and I you know my love for
Africa naturally run so deep so I had
always had this also just for you know
my sensitivity around privilege the deep
quandary around privilege that has been
a part of my life story and I think it's
at the heart of the deepest trauma that
is currently ripping the world apart you
know currently in the US but in so many
places is the story of privilege and
unintegrated trauma of the past that we
carry that keeps recreating inequity in
our world in deeper and deeper ways but
so my yes of my engagement with Gaia
education and bringing out the Eco
village design education super
passionate about this spreading the
knowledge of how to create community how
to regenerate ecosystems how to
regenerate cultures how to regenerate
economic systems and teach that in depth
has been was a part of my life already
at that time and I'd also just happen to
be at at the board meeting the
International gen board meeting in 2007
I ended up facilitating that with inna
Meyer stole from zeg in Thailand so I
was you know I was cleared into gen for
a while
I really I have some beautiful
conversations of the two of us at that
meeting would you be okay if I shared
them also conversations with ena and
everybody who was a I just just thought
it was interesting to tell a little bit
more about that time that led up to you
being elected because I always felt from
the distance at the time I was at
Finland that what you were doing in
Linton was really fascinating by really
pioneering a path to connection with the
German government and international
development aid to get people and to
have them I think it was much fun some
places on the e de well I think it was a
gift that was brought to me so I was in
this eco village in Germany in linen
which was based on a foundation of
radical ecological simplicity so based
on the Club of Rome report limits to
growth and wanting to bring down the
ecological footprint to 30 and even 10%
of German average and I was living in
the most radical neighborhoods so the
Eco village is now around a hundred
fifty a hundred seventy people but
organized in neighborhoods and the most
radical neighbourhood at that time was
called the club 99 so we were living in
an area where we just trialed building a
house without any electricity just with
horsepower and only with materials from
the immediate vicinity so the would you
know SOI to get through with all German
sores Hansel's you know my my little son
was helping to trample the mud for the
walls and we ended up with a house that
was below 10% of the energy resources
that a house uses in Germany of a
similar size but also we lived in an
area where nothing that was wrapped and
plastic was allowed to be brought in
nothing that had been wrapped in plastic
so nothing beyond local production we
act locally and I lived that life for
four to five years you know I love to do
things in cycles and really get a deep
taste of it I didn't fly for seven years
I refused to fly so I remember traveling
by train up Tiffin Turin and you know
anything because we both did the no fly
thing for about seven years at a time
where very few people did it and then I
got a lot of stick afterwards when he
got fashionable we decided to fly for
other reason yeah I and I always had a
global heart I think you know I just
carried in within me you know having
been born and grown up in South Africa
lived in different countries and I think
I have a I am an African you know my
body is African even though I have a
white skin it's it's I connect to the
nature deep in the soil to the animals
to the class to the sounds in the air
like South Africa is my physical home in
the world there's no question about that
you know so I just carry this love and
heart for Africa especially but coming
from Africa for the world and I was
fascinated whenever we had the chance of
inviting and global friends to come and
visit that was when my heart was was
beating and I became fascinated by the
fact that we were for instant using
draught animals inseam linen horses my
best friend was this horse whisperer
soldier and we had people coming to us
from say Colombia or Venezuela or Ghana
or India who were saying oh we're just
getting rid of our draught animals you
know and we're just replacing them with
tractors and we were saying well
actually you know how this will stamp
down the soil and here in Germany we're
just
introducing draught animals in some of
the farms because in terms of
sequestering carbon in the soil and non
tilled soil you know it can be wonderful
to work with animals in that way so you
know we had people coming saying watch
you build your houses with straw and mud
and you're proud of it you know you've
just been to our countries teaching us
to use cement you know now we come here
and you're proud of this you know you're
proud that you grow 80 percent of your
own vegetables you know shall I laugh or
cry you know this was the kind of
responses we were getting and I just
loved it you know I loved it we talked
about this before before I had a kind of
similar key experience teaching the
first été and once ended after that
meeting they were just talked about and
having somebody who was a village leader
from a I think a Christian group in the
north of of niyama and after giving a
talk on here I images from eco villages
all around the world showing some of the
flagships and some of the smaller ones
and and kind of talking about the
patterns and and John Gilman's first
report and all those kind of things he
came up to me after the talk with a
silly sight so the hesitation in his
voice it was like if what you just
showed me way ecovillages then all our
villages are eco villages yeah and I
said yes and this this and this this
moment of recognition
north south that so much of what the
North has thrown out baby with the
bathwater of patterns the routier in
landscape that route you to your health
through food that you do ecosystem and
that make you indigenous to place in
inhabit place patterns that we know
desperately seeking to reinvent recover
and reconnect with in the global north
and giving just that function that jen
has had of encouraging people in the
global south to say these patterns are
valuable patterns and don't make the
mistake of just because
Media pretend you all have to look like
a Californian um you don't yeah that's
exactly it so that's the trick you know
that's the exploration that I got so
involved in so you know just from that
inspiration I started inviting people
from the global south as much as
possible to come to the course and the
connection to the German Foreign
Ministry actually grew out of that so I
started just by using my own funds and
doing and collecting private donations
from friends you know I really wasn't a
fundraiser but I learned to be a
fundraiser over the years is also a
lesson in there because you created a
pattern that you could then point to
when you asked for the phone exactly
they're just going to say so in 2009 I
went to cop15 in Copenhagen which was
the disaster cop as some people call it
we're all negotiations broke down and
you know one friend who's stayed a close
friend of mine over all these years who
is there to negotiate as part of the
German delegation he had been to one of
our presentations to a few of our
presentations and I started
conversations with him afterwards
because he was so deeply disappointed
that he said we need to start doing
something different and this is the
other pattern that is very important
that there are good people everywhere
amazing we spread ourselves you know I
wouldn't say thinly but we are
everywhere so the people of regeneration
are not just in gen and the permaculture
movement they sit in governments they
sit in corporations and we just need to
seek each other out because I would say
you know even going deeper than that
it's not the people but the places in
people that beat for regeneration I
would say those places are alive in
every person and we just need to connect
to them and bring them out and it
the most joyful creative heart
fulfilling impulse to give to life it's
the act that brings joy and satisfaction
and fulfillment to our lives that brings
out our potential in life so you know
this is what we can give to each other
what the movement of regeneration gives
but I want to come back to my story
sorry so um yeah so you know I could
already share images also from people in
the global South connecting to a German
eco village teaching us you know we had
this amazing indigenous woman for
instance from IRISA come to the
equivalent of Germany in the
introductory round everybody says where
they are from she shares I am from the
forest I come from the soil and I will
return to the soil my name is the name
of a bird species who lives in our
forests because these are the beings
that I am most closely family with you
know and then you know she was shy
because she couldn't write as well her
English wasn't well she had never been
to official schooling and but she knew
how to make 40 kinds of compost from cow
manure how to make herbicides from cow
urine she could recognize more herbs and
teach us about their health qualities
than we could you know so the the deep
touchid nosov really touching into the
depth of indigenous knowledge systems
you know install I just want to say one
more sentence when we speak about
ecosystem restoration when we speak
about indigenous wisdom as referring to
the ecosystems we are only touching the
surface and we need to realize that that
the deep connectedness that lies at the
heart of indigenous wisdom or at the
heart of belonging to the planet goes
far beyond ecosystem restoration
absolutely.i in a conversation with John
Fullerton a couple of months ago somehow
the simplicity of the framing that where
we went wrong was when we stopped
understanding that we belong to the
earth and started believing that the
earth could possibly belong to us and
that is really at the heart of all
indigenous wisdom cultures but it isn't
just an intellectual thought it is a
complete other way of being when when
you feel yourself as an expression of
landscape like like you were just
describing the this woman
expressing her relations and I think
maybe even to state it quite a little
bit differently I am an expression of
landscape yes and my nervous system is
part of the planet young planet E and
beyond planet exactly
yes I'm wondering you know because I
also see time flying I'm wondering how
to tell you know a little history of Jen
in a short time but there's one thing
that I wanted to briefly go get back to
because on the one hand is it it is
interesting that in this founding moment
at Finland at that conference and there
wasn't enough representation of the
global South but to be fair to the the
emergence of that moment and the
conference wasn't called to create Jen
and the conference brought a bunch of
people together that that then decided
now that we're all together we we should
create Jen like there it was it was kind
of almost a rushed like the way I've
always had it told from from the the
Musketeers that were there Declan
Kennedy and other Bates and Matt slim
bigger and
it was sort of to lazin to the
conference that they decided can we draw
up the founding impulse for the global
eco village network yeah I mean it was
called the equivalent conference right
communities for the 21st century
yeah exactly but eco village was very
quiet but also I think we're not
speaking here about criticizing that
first conference much more were speaking
about you know a founding seed and how
the patterns of an emerging network are
visible in the founding seed right and
Jen was founded by a circle of white
Western people and even more so white
Western men there were women involved
but the more visible circle of
leadership at the beginning was white
Western men and I think that is also
honest to own that a part of the you
know part of the transformation that I
was a part of I was the first female
president of Gen I was the first female
CEO of Gen not the first female
president of Gen Europe but of the
global ecology network or the the
president meaning chair of Trustees just
but you know there there was a shift
also to somehow from a circle of masks
wonderful men wonderful man you know
this is Albert Bates max Limburger and
Declan Kennedy wonderful men you know
Ross Jackson and killed her Jackson in
the background and then there was me
East stepping up and guy education and
then myself stepping up in Gen and I've
been in very visible leadership in gen
for the past 12 years in varying roles
but very visible and it's interesting
that at this point in time both maiice
and I are stepping out and I hope that
more collaborative leadership models are
also being developed in both
organization but so that was one journey
we could speak more about but the other
journey in gen has
being from and again we had global self
represented for instance through
Sarvodaya which was a strong founding
member and was very present where
traditional villages were honored from
the out start engine as eco villages but
there was a time in especially 2008 to
2012 where that was a part of my main
work engine was to find a framework of
recognition both for traditional
villages as eco villages and intentional
communities as eco villages urban
communities as eco villages and rural
communities as eco villages so that but
especially the traditional communities
to bring those voices in to honor them
because one thing is to know that
they're there another thing is to bring
their voice to the table and to bring
the learning to the table really
supported the whole what then led to the
foundation of gen Africa instead of
having that strange putting Europe and
Africa into one Secretariat and and also
like the supports of that gen activities
in Africa really brought all these
stories of the Senegal Network and I
mean it's amazing what Jen has then
catalyzed by linking local peoples good
work not by coming in and doing the work
but by enabling and linking and
supporting people in Africa to work
together yes sir when I was invited in
in 2008 I was explicitly but invited in
with my passion to work towards the
emergence of Gen Africa so I was part of
you know and the interesting thing was
that that you could say
mobilization of Jain Europe you know I
know we speak about glocalization and I
realize you know I mean that's that is
the important thing is to stay very very
rooted in the local and spreading out
but by inviting the global networks to
the European conferences we grew these
conferences from 80 I believe 70 or 80
the first conference I was up to seven
hundred eight hundred seven years later
so real beautiful growth of interest
simply and in parallel through those
eco-village design education that we
just spoke through should being able to
show the first example we were able to
attract professional support for the
courses we were then able to invite more
people to come to the Eco village design
education courses from Africa and I you
know because they are already the
networks are often already existing
mouth-to-mouth who's the person who's
doing most community-led work
regenerative work on the ground in
Malawi
everybody knows you know and you can go
in through seven seven portals through
our network and the same names may be
mentioned right so finding those people
wasn't so hard
and inviting them and there was a huge
sense of synergy of resonance of
recognition and then the beautiful
moment came first in 2011 with the Arab
Spring where I got a call from the
German Foreign Minister saying actually
we have 70 thousand euro left over and
we know that you're doing some work in
Africa could you arrange something in
North Africa and I said yes
and so that was kind of the pre gen
Africa conference where we could invite
people from Tunisia Morocco Algeria
Egypt Sudan just to come together in
Sikkim and then 2012 we were able to
replicate that conference but inviting
all these people 80 people from around
Africa 90
sent of whom had completed an IDI and
semen and that was just absolutely
mind-blowing I have never experienced
anything like it where a conference
happened where people who didn't know
each other had all been steeped in the
same knowledge community and they could
recognize the language and within five
days we drafted the vision the mission
the goals and it was just an explosion
of creativity the most beautiful I can
Africa you know it's grown slowly
because Africa is not an easy continent
to bridge electronically especially if
you work with grassroots communities but
that founding impulse for Gen Africa was
just stunning a star so I still think
Jed Africa will go very far
yeah and at the same time the Latin
American network was founded Casa latina
which I've been in conversation with but
you know they just decided look this is
it were we're breaking loose from the
North American networks and we're
wanting to do our thing in Spanish
because we are Spanish and Portuguese
we're not English and that became Casa
so you'd had the same similar dimension
to it which is the power of a very
diverse white I mean you were involved
in developing the original été
curriculum that holistic map that
Mandela of the four dimensions and that
process of at least opening the window
on so many interrelated aspects from
nonviolent communications to how to
write a business plan to how to create a
vision statement to dragon dreaming to
in permaculture to sewage free treatment
systems and it just gives people a
shared knowledge map and in a shared
experience that then makes it so much
easier to connect them to work together
and I've seen this when I when I went to
Brazil and met so many of the the guy on
OHS in Brazil to see how they are linked
up and down the country and have done
lots of diverse things since but it's so
much easier to work together because
they have that shared experience and I
think also drew on that as well and I
think in a lesser to a lesser degree
anybody who has visited an eco village
especially one of the more established
eco villages carries that seed within
them so the amount of change making that
has grown out of eco villages you know
we now link to 6090 communities in the
world that we can you know know what the
the we have the geographical data we
have the connecting person for all these
people all these communities were linked
to the global eco village network as
communities that are dedicated to
becoming sustainable or being
sustainable all of these communities are
churning out changemakers anybody who
comes and visits and leaves again says
this has changed my life and then the
eco village design education courses are
like a cherry on the cake you know if
you come to a four-week course like that
an immersion course you leave every
single person has told me I'm forever
changed so it's an incredible change
making movement because that is going on
it's their incubators for whole host of
projects that grow up in them and around
them they then create the first patterns
for what would an ecosystems restoration
camp look like I mean the the big
established eco villages know that
because they've been engaged somebody
who used the ferment of the eco village
to launch an organization where there
was trees for life and Alan Watts in
Featherstone and fintan oh it was all
the wonderful work that they've done in
Oroville
so many other the mangrove forest
regeneration in Senegal and they're just
so many experiences that you can then
not just talk about by pointer and
that's
the transformative aspect of learning in
ecovillages that that he also connect to
real on-the-ground projects that that
have a bit of a track record and and can
inspire people to say this is possible
I'm gonna do this in my region and in my
way with my community in and and
sensitivity to the place that that we're
in
yes and every eco village is an
ecosystem restoration settlement you
know I love i I just remember that there
was this scientific research done on
biodiversity in the zeg community in a
local city like it's it's a small town
like a local external neighborhood and
then a rural area including forests and
everything and the biodiversity was so
much higher within the eco village you
know so just to say every eco village is
an ecosystem restoration community or a
village yeah it's because we I think
we're both in our journeys of on the one
hand deeply believing in the very local
community grounded work of trying to
live sustainably close to the land and
we also care about how does this pattern
spread into the wider society and how do
we include everybody including the the
millions and of people living in in
dense cities and and in what I'm
noticing right now is that there's a big
push again there's almost like a new
wave of people waking up to that initial
impulse that might have brought you and
me close to eco villages many years ago
where which might be a bit more at a
certain phase in life you you just want
to get together with a group of people
you feel akin to and just do the project
and and build the community and em but
it but it can have that little bit of
energy of Jen collapsing into the
hyperlocal to the point that you lose
soon with the global and I think we both
care that that pendulum swing doesn't
happen so much that people can find
their local grounding place but that we
keep open that the global pattern and
how do you see that
dynamic of ultimately we need to all
localize in order to shift not just
doing patterns but being patterns deeply
in US and at the same time we also still
need to find ways of maintaining global
solidarity collaboration knowledge
exchange and connection in order to
enable that favori body around the globe
where do you see Jen if if you sort of
dream into the highest potential now
that you're slowly moving out of the
leadership role in Jen where would you
see gently play role in maintaining that
local dynamic yeah I would love to just
go back to the history and complete that
first and it leads there anywhere anyway
so it's a perfect perfect common to
bring in so you know with Jen Africa and
Casa having emerged we had finally more
of a global voice engine and from the
beginning the global eco village network
was there as a idea and organization at
the time I stepped it in it was a
pro-forma
Italian NGO that Hart didn't even have a
bank account anymore so it was really
non-existent and it had an International
Board that tried to meet in person once
a year and going to the most beautiful
places around the planet very lucky
people that was before my time and but
really the work was done through the
three big regions so eco village Network
of the Americas enna and Jane Europe
Middle East and Africa and Genoa
which was
old in Australia and with the growth of
June Africa and casas with it bringing
out of those voices also to the European
conferences which were the biggest
gatherings the biggest conferences we
suddenly had a different presence around
the table it was also much more maxilla
nigger stepped out and we had new people
stepping in from Asia which really
brought the Asian boy strongly so my
next piece of work what I was dedicated
to was also setting up Jen
the global part of the network as a
strong charity and I at that time I had
moved to fin torn fin torrents seemed
like the perfect place you know where
the founding of Jan the celebration of
Jen's 10th year anniversary had taken
place here so in 2013 Jen was founded as
a Scottish charity and from that point
on we had a clear Constitution outlining
that each of the regions would have
equal representation to the board would
have equal representation to the General
Assembly and Jen became a real conscious
expression of global culture you know we
have 45 representatives to our General
Assembly and they come from probably 43
different countries so when we have our
General Assemblies we span the globe and
we hear the voices from around the globe
and that is something incredibly
precious and I find you know just coming
back to my own life when we speak about
so that's one one aspect of globality is
actually listening to the voices and I
see a great struggle around this or
confusion I would say we're also I'm
often now say in environments where
indigenous voices are there
and it becomes hard sometimes for other
voices to be heard right
because it's it's very it's a huge
exploration how to listen and which are
the voices that need to be heard at what
time at which time and how we how do we
allow how do we allow the world to truly
speak to us through human voices but
also through all the other feedback
systems of the world so listening to the
world you know is is super important in
Jin and super important in all of our
work of course just a brief question for
you personally because and there's a
little bit of a parallel not that I
haven't grown up in Africa but I've also
lived in very different cultures but
that ability that like you grew up in
South Africa you spend a lot of time in
Germany no you spend a lot of time in
Scottish culture and I spent a long time
in Holland I lived seven years in
Holland yeah so so it's this um having
actually lived in lots of different
cultural contexts and seeing how 'days
is a different uniqueness by a cultural
uniqueness of each place and and each
culture is that how is that informing
you your work and do you think it's
important for people to have if they're
privileged enough to care in to be able
to do so this this multicultural yeah so
I feel like we have two topics now on
the table one is about scaling up and
this is another topic so I just want to
Park or scaling out so I just want to
park that one consciously
so you know it's lovely you speak to
that because I'd love I've been wanting
to come to that you know also speaking
about flying because yes it's been it's
been deeply transformative for me to
have lived in these different cultural
contexts and you know I to be
I my sense is that all of us have
nervous systems I just want to say that
before I go into the rest I think that
our nervous systems have and we know
this scientifically also that we have
a far greater capacity to receive
information from the world around us
than we are working with and at the
heart of regeneration to me lies the
opening of our capacity to receive the
information that is necessary to be able
to respond adequately we are not able to
respond adequately when our nervous
systems are shut down and our nervous
systems are shut down not I mean that's
too absolute but they're shut down in
places and that's that's an issue of
compassion what it needs is compassion
and healing because there's a good a
very good reason for a nervous systems
not to be open but to come back to my
cultural experience growing up in South
Africa my nervous system as a child was
able to read the field I had I grew up
in a relatively conservative bula family
speaking Afrikaans which is my language
of Wiccans which believed that apartheid
was the only way to keep us safe as a
family as a nation Afrikaner
and I grew up with a sense of the field
with dreams about the reality of
apartheid with a sense of the growing
wave of anger and injustice I could feel
it in every cell of my body as a child
and yes I did see a few images in my
childhood which brought it home so
starkly there was no way as a child in
South Africa that I wouldn't have been
able to see the system you know and
there was a heavy um there was a heavy
way
that the system was portrayed to us as
children at school you know history
started with fondly biack landing in
Cape Town you know there was a very
specific way the history was taught to
us or the reasons why the system was in
place so waking up to that the injustice
being felt on a physical level without a
system responding to it adequately
without being allowed to speak about my
sensory perceptions what I experienced I
find that that that same reality is
replicated to a globally to all of us
you know as our sensory apparatus our
nervous system reads what we are doing
to the planet and I believe that we are
much more able to do that than we
consciously know I believe we are doing
it much more than we are consciously
know the rising levels of depression are
one expression of that you know and
again if we align ourselves with what we
know is right and wrong wherever we are
we find our pathway it's like the red
thread right
so having lived in these different
countries was one entrance door the
other entrance start from he came with a
flying and the fact that I have now
worked in 48 different countries around
the world most of them in the global
South many many of them in the global
cell and I have when I've worked I've
mostly worked in communities on the
ground so I've had that experience you
know I've had the experience of going to
the United Nations Climate Change
Conference watching governments speak
about stopping the logging down of trees
and then traveling through a country
like say Ghana or Zambia and just
watching the trucks roll out with the
biggest oldest most beautiful trees you
know being in The Gambia watching the
tracks roll out with a
from the sand dunes well at the same
time the sea levels are rising and the
government knows that these religious
are directly threatened by sea level
rise and still the sand is being shipped
out to the rest of the world I've been
watching the the the waste from Europe
being brought into Africa you know all
of this is visible on the ground
if you travel and you don't travel to
their touristic hotels but you actually
travel the countries you travel the
world there you know I can see the
destruction of our ecosystems as we
speak about ecosystem restoration and I
feel like maybe I've just come to a time
in my life where I've seen it I have
felt it I've come home time after time
after time bringing hope to these places
supporting the growth of regenerative
communities on the ground and come home
with a breaking heart and a need to more
in deeply for what is happening to our
planet and I feel like somehow this
locked down and the coronavirus it's
just you know the timing is so exquisite
I interviewed my good friend Miss Elena
Mises one of the elders from Namibia in
January for the communities for future
summit the global ecology Network summit
where she said we just need everything
to stop all the machines all the
airplanes everything needs to stop just
for a moment so we can breathe in so we
can actually come back to the land and
think what on earth are we doing
and then coronavirus come you know some
people I wouldn't say it's her doing but
I do think that some people have been
tapping into the need for a time of
reflection you know the need for a kind
of a bit of a shock treatment - you know
I would say the opposite of a shock
treatment because the slowing down has
allowed our nerve
systems also to slow down and I know
that it's yeah it's going in many
different directions but for me
personally I feel that I have gathered
an incredible amount of information I
couldn't be more grateful for the love
relationships that I have built across
the globe the beauty of the people that
I have met in these networks you know
because this is about love and it's not
an abstract love it's my love for Linda
Kabira in Zimbabwe it's my love for
Sunita from Cameroon it's my love for
magatha for Paul from Ghana it's my love
for Jennifer from Colombia for margarita
and Evan from the islands in Colombia
you know it's the love for the people in
Sri Lanka or Thailand or you know it's
our love for each other that matters and
there's something where we can build
that love through zoom we can deepen
that love through zoom but we're just
learning to do that we're just learning
to actually open a true being of nervous
systems together through zoom and we're
still it's still easier for us to do it
in human to human connectedness so we're
learning now right but that love is the
basis for to humanity to emerge so I
could not be more grateful to KLM to the
possibility to travel and I think it's
really hard if you live in one place all
your life to grasp the global reality we
have an incredible resource brought to
us though which is the refugees
traveling the world and they are
doorways right they bring the world to
our doorstep what a gift so sitting
with each other and not just touching
the surface but going truly deep eating
eating each other's food listening to
the cultural stories listening to the
true pain watching the images the
photographs the history of the countries
you know this is what will bring us home
to ourselves so I believe this is super
necessary and maybe I can go to the
scaling out and scaling up oh we're at
the end of our time what you've just
said is really a wonderful place to and
but at the same time there's so much
more we could talk about I just would
like to bond Lincoln to you your next
steps from that because you've shared
beautifully your passion for Jen and and
the people that that is because Jen is
just a name but it's the people that you
were able to connect with all around the
world that that hold that impulse and
and and and spread it em and give it for
so long also drawn very strongly from
your work with Thomas who work and I
understand your next step with the
pocket project brings you also closer to
working with with him even more and what
he just spoke to this on the one hand is
the central reconnecting to our ability
to be empathic and loving to our wider
family in to to life and I have always
admired that for a long time you've been
through Thomas's work working with those
blocks that shut up off our nervous
system so the trauma work and the deeper
work of patterns and and Stan the pocket
project also tries to work with that can
you say a little bit more about your
personal next yeah you know I think that
just in the global ecology Network I
have also been in that tension of the
local and the global
my tenancy was always very much to go
out there to say look we need to we need
to give Jin to the world we need to open
up to the globe you know that's been
mine and there is another part engine
which is very much about the local and I
love my garden you know it's not the
content of my work in the world but I
completely love my carrots growing in my
beans and my cucumbers at the moment so
that but that tension between giving
enough space for the localization
impulse and the opening impulse for
going out and how to really bring those
together that's part of the shift that
I'm making and the other part of the
shift is just seeing again and again how
in our movement of regeneration we hit
ceilings so we give everything and we do
amazing work in ecosystem restoration
camps in eco villages but we hit
ceilings in the social and I've watched
this over time so I've watched
communities develop really beautifully
to a certain level and then it feels
like they start circling and I've been
wondering about this and the next level
of creativity is on the edge of those
communities I've really been wondering
about that and I've written a book on
collective wisdom in Germany exploring
what is collective wisdom at that time I
asked the question and what is
collective stupidity and I would ask how
is collective wisdom linked to
collective and intergenerational trauma
and as you say for me the edges of our
region regeneration movement are where
we hit the places in our nervous system
that are not open to receiving feedback
that are not open to be inspired by an
intelligence that is bigger than us and
I would say the deepest wind that we
carry is believing that this sack of
skin is Who I am and we know that we're
more but I don't think we have an idea
of just what
actually means what the web of life that
we are woven into that we are not on top
of we are a deep expression of it and we
will indeed go back to it yeah what that
means and so now I feel like it's about
you could say the job of cleaning the
pipes so that the energy of inspiration
and creativity can run more freely
through the nervous system of humanity I
believe deeply that we are here on the
planet as guardians of life that we are
here to express our beauty in extremely
unique ways where each individual is a
king or a queen of our own unique
expression and at the same time that
being a perfect synchronistic unique
contribution to the whole and if each
one of us gives our piece to the whole
there is no too much to do for anyone so
the clean up of our nervous systems that
we need to be able to do that that's
what I'm fascinated by next and many
people get a bit like Oh God working
with collective trauma that sounds very
dark and daunting to me it's like it's
the most exciting journey ever that's
where the pearls are waiting to be
that's where the light is waiting to be
unveiled you know so I'm just super
excited also it's also the most deeply
regenerative work because it is the
regenerative work of understanding that
in healing those places in us you heal
the larger it goes beyond the humanity
nature dualism that runs so deep in our
culture it understands that if we would
truly want to become
expressions of life creating conditions
conducive to life
again we need we need to deal with with
with these wounds and the way you just
described this this dance-off air
enabling everyone to shine in expressing
their full unique potential that only
they in the whole history of life on
earth and humanity have has only been
one moment for that person to be that
person in the best way possible
and and that in doing so in service to
the larger that's where the nourishment
comes from the larger that enables that
individual to do that so it's this this
dynamic tension that life has full of
living in this illusion of consciousness
of being for oneself and being part part
of a larger whole that I find this is
where the conscious evolutionary
participation in this process is what
we're stepping into when we're talking
about true regeneration son I'm super
excited that you I I really honor you
for for what you've already seated in
the world and I feel that that special
period before you could move to vent on
that we spoke about a little bit where
these bees were happening from Stephen
Linton I know that I've met lots of
people that were deeply touched by what
do you enabled with those courses we
haven't had much time to talk about how
Paulo and the lush connection and and
all eating in a visionary company into
supporting this kind of work as we
talked about bringing in the German
government but you are an arch Weaver
and I see you we could go on for a long
longer but this has been beautiful and
thank you so much thank you so much
Daniel a real joy speaking to you yeah
and I look forward to in an interesting
way connecting to more people
all through this video when it goes out
so interesting right how we connect to
so many people my little meekness and
the global family it's beautiful this is
my little way of trying to find the
rhythm with actually going local like
local like I feel a very strong clarity
now that my daughter's very young still
and of course yes before she legally has
to go to school whether we do
homeschooling or not is another question
that is open but I really want to spend
the next three years deepening my roots
here and and spending time with my
daughter planting trees and and and
building a home and and so I'm a little
bit in this day how do I do that without
like how do I disconnect a little bit
from that amazing work that is out there
that can be done weaving networks and
people together and and just coming home
to reason nourish and and just go
through that cycle in the trust that um
there'll be times to be more globally
focused again for me but but right now I
need to come home to the soil and I
think the same might happen for me it
just feels like well this is the shift
I'm going to after being away for more
than 50% of my time for the past 10 15
years I'm going to be staying home and
connecting globally Thank You Daniel go
well all the best
much love